בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is י"ז Yud Zayin and
we are close to being caught up. We are on ט"ז עמוד
ב' Tet Zayin amud bet in the middle of a short דף
Daf and this actually quite some very central and important topics that
are about to be coming up and dealing with a major concern
of מסכת יבמות, Masechet Yevamot, which is not יבום Yibum per se
but issues of personal status in general. And so let's take a
look. And we've already begun this because the גמרא Gemara yesterday introduced
the idea of a testimony from חגי הנביא Chaggai HaNavi number one,
that צרת הבת Tsaras HaBat is מותרת, muteret, the position of
בית הלל, Beit Hillel, but also number two, that the people living
in these two places, תרמוד Tarmod and
קרדויים, Karduyim, one can accept גרים, geirim, which means that one assumes
that they're non-Jews as opposed to apparently what was a concern that
they might have been Jews and ממזרים. Mamzerim. And then you could
not accept גרים geirim from them; they wouldn't need גירות, geirus, but
they would still have the problem of ממזרות mamzerut which cannot be
solved. And now and then the גמרא Gemara had a contradiction of
statements of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan whether you could or could not
accept converts from תרמוד, Tarmod, and that's where we left off. And
now we're going to look at what actually the issues were. So
on ט"ז עמוד ב' Tet Zayin amud bet we have the following:
מאי
טעמא? Mai Ta'ama? Six lines down, beginning of the line.
טעמא?
Mai
Ta'ama? מיתרמוד מאי טעמא לא? Mi-Tarmod mai ta'ama lo? One word before
that. מיתרמוד מאי טעמא לא? Mi-Tarmod mai ta'ama lo? Why can you
not accept for those that say you cannot or what's the potential
problem of accepting converts from תרמוד? Tarmod? פליגי ביה רבי יוחנן וסביא.
Pligi beih Rabbi Yochanan v'Savia. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and סביא, Savia,
a person we saw yesterday, very rare אמורא, Amora, they debate this.
חד אמר משום עבדי שלמה. Chad amar mishum avdei Shlomo. One says
because of the servants of שלמה Shlomo who were not Jewish, who
apparently married women from תרמוד. Tarmod. Okay, so women who are Jewish
women who are descendants of non-Jews, even non-Jewish servants, should still be
Jewish. What's the issue? Not clear what the issue would be. וחד
אמר משום בנות ירושלים, V'chad amar mishum bnot Yerushalayim, the young women
of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. We'll see what that means in the context of
what happened after the חורבן בית המקדש, Churban Beit HaMikdash, but also
again, if they've got a Jewish mother, what should the problem be?
I mean, especially if we suggested that the issue is ממזרות. mamzerut.
So not exactly clear what the issues are. So let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. בשלמא למאן דאמר משום עבדי שלמה, Bishlama
l'man d'amar mishum avdei Shlomo, it works according to the one who
says the problem is the servants of שלמה. Shlomo. קסבר
עובד כוכבים ועבד הבא על בת ישראל הולד ממזר. Kasavar oveid kochavim
v'eved haba al bat yisrael havlad mamzer. Now this is a pretty
shocking idea to us, right? A non-Jew and a Jewish woman, the
child, well, we're all used to saying okay, matrilineal descent, the child
is Jewish, end of story. But actually here's a position that the
child is a ממזר, mamzer, or a slave with a non-Jewish woman,
the child is a ממזר. mamzer. What is this about? So תוספות,
Tosafot, this big תוספות קסבר, Tosafot Kasavar, first argues that this is
a function of רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position that there is a
ממזר מחיובי לאוין, mamzer m'chiyuvei lavin, that a child that comes from
an איסור, issur, a
sexual prohibition even a simple negative commandment, the child is a ממזר.
mamzer. And that's what it's based on. But then תוספות Tosafot says
one minute, that works for עבד eved because at least according to
a certain פסוק pasuk is read to understand that there's a negative
prohibition to have sex with a slave, but non-Jew actually, ironically, although
on the one hand it's been thought of as the worst sin,
people marry out, they lose their Jewish identity, parents would sit שבעה
shiva and so on, from a technical perspective,
the actual prohibition of sex with a non-Jew might actually only be
דרבנן. d'rabanan. On the other hand, the גמרא Gemara says that if
somebody has sex with a non-Jew in public, קנאים פוגעים בו, kanai'im
pog'im bo, like the story of פנחס, Pinchas, but if it's not
in public and the actual technical prohibition might not be biblical if
it's not one of the
שבעה עממים, shiva amamin, seven Canaanite nations. So תוספות Tosafot says so
why would the child be a ממזר? mamzer? So one answer he
has is well, maybe it only be a ממזר מדרבנן. mamzer mid'rabanan.
Okay fine. But then he has another answer which points us to
something not about רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and not about the איסור
issur of just a transgression of a לאו. lav. So if you
let's take a look at the middle of תוספות קסבר, Tosafot Kasavar,
he says like this. He
says ואם תאמר, V'im tomar, if you go from the next תוספות
פסוק Tosafot pasuk and you go one, two, three, four, five, five
lines. Line starts with the word על בת ישראל הולד ממזר ועל
כרחך רבי עקיבא היא. Al bat yisrael havlad mamzer v'al korchacha Rabbi
Akiva hi. So then it says ואם תאמר V'im tomar about a
third into that line. People see that? Yeah? Yeah? ואם תאמר, V'im
tomar, yeah, תוספות Tosafot you see five lines above where it says
פסוק. pasuk. next תוספות Tosfos and then go about a third in
where it says ואם תאמר. v'im tomar. Yeah. ואם תאמר v'im tomar
בשלמא מעבד הוי ממזר דבעבד איכא לאו אלא מעובד כוכבים אמאי הוי
ממזר
bishlema me-eved havai mamzer d'v'eved ika lav ela
me-oved kochavim amai havai mamzer בית דין של שם גזרו. Beis Din
shel Shem gazru. That's a rabbinic. ומהתורה ביאת היתר היא u'me-d'oraisa bias
heter hi which again is quite shocking to us, but then and
that's not to downplay at all the
profound sociological and identity significance of it, but technically if that's true
the child shouldn't be a ממזר. mamzer. ויש לומר v'yesh lomar אף
על גב af al gav דביאת היתר היא de-bias heter hi מהתורה
me-d'oraisa בצנעא b'tzina as long as it's in private public is קנאים
פוגעים בו kanaim pogim bo מכל מקום mi'kol makom כיון דלא תפסי
בה קידושין keivan de-lo tafsi bah kiddushin הוי ממזר havai mamzer כמו
בעבד k'mo b'eved that's really not about being a לאו lav it
really is about the fact
that קידושין kiddushin is not possible. So most of the time when
you have
איסורי לאוין, issurei lavin, מחזיר גרושתו, machzir grushaso, אשת יבם לשוק, eshes
yavam lashuk, so the one of the major difference between an איסור
לאו issur lav and an איסור כרת issur kares is that an
איסור לאו issur lav even though it's prohibited if you do the
act of קידושין kiddushin it takes effect. The woman is actually married.
In איסור כרת issur kares she's not. So what תוספות Tosfos points
out is you could have a situation where there could be no
קידושין kiddushin even if it's not an איסור. issur. What would be
a situation that no קידושין kiddushin even though it's not an איסור?
issur? With a non-Jew. Maybe there's no לאו lav but nevertheless the
תורה Torah doesn't recognize the act of קידושין kiddushin with a non-Jew.
So what he says is maybe it has nothing to do with
רבי עקיבא. Rebbe Akiva. Maybe it has nothing to do with a
לאו. lav. Maybe in certain way it's more similar to the כרת
kares idea not because the weight of the transgression but because there's
no possibility of קידושין kiddushin and that maybe is what this is
what the identity of a ממזר mamzer is. ממזר mamzer is not
a child that was produced through a transgression of a לאו lav
or a כרת. kares. Maybe according to this idea ממזר mamzer is
a child that is produced through a union in which קידושין kiddushin
could never take effect. Yes.
Why דווקא davka a Jewish woman and a non-Jewish man? It doesn't
matter.
No, because if it was a non-Jewish woman the child wouldn't be
Jewish. So it would be a moot point.
Although could the child be able to
convert normally and then be a ממזר? mamzer? Yes. From that perspective
the answer is yes. Now we're going to get to that case
in a minute so just hold on. Okay?
And then he goes right.
Okay. And then fine, so that's basically the תוספות's Tosfos's answer and
then he says maybe it's only מדרבנן. mi'drabbanan. So we have this
radical idea which we don't פסקן pasken the first part of תוספות
Tosfos we don't פסקן pasken this way thank God right because then
because then we'd have instead of having conversion issues with patrilineal descent
we'd have ממזרות mamzerus issues and as was just pointed out conversion
issues are easier than ממזרות mamzerus issues conversion issues can be solved.
So number one just that we don't פסקן pasken this way. But
number two this idea that the child of a non-Jew and a
non-Jewish man and a Jewish woman is a ממזר mamzer is it
based on a רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva idea that there's a transgression
of a לאו lav and therefore it's just a very broad definition
of ממזר mamzer which we don't פסקן pasken like but again applies
to any transgression of a לאו lav or is it unique to
the idea of עבד eved and non-Jew and has nothing to do
with the לאו lav has to do with the fact that the
union is not קידושין kiddushin is not possible in the union which
is in the case of all the איסורי כרת issurei kares as
well. Okay so that's a way of understanding this not based on
רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva and more similar to the idea of ממזר
mamzer from a prohibition of כרת kares because that also is a
type of a marriage which קידושין kiddushin is not possible. Yes.
What would a ממזר מדרבנן mamzer mi'drabbanan be?
Well we'll have that and we'll get to it. Okay. But by
the way I'll give you another example of a child that's the
product of an איסור כרת issur kares that isn't a ממזר. mamzer.
Do you know what that is? Child that was נידה. niddah. Exactly.
So you could have an איסור
כרת issur kares act of sex that's איסור כרת issur kares that
doesn't produce a ממזר mamzer נידה niddah because obviously קידושין kiddushin is
possible in that context and might even be present in that context.
And you could have a child of a no prohibition altogether that
is a ממזר mamzer according to this opinion which is non-Jew because
there's no קידושין. kiddushin. So תוספות Tosfos is pointing us to the
idea that ממזר mamzer might more have to do with the impossibility
of קידושין kiddushin than with the actual weight of the transgression. And
like I said luckily we don't פסקן pasken this way. We פסקן
pasken the child is just simply not
Jewish I'm sorry the child is Jewish excuse
me matrilineal descent
non-Jewish father the child is just simply Jewish. So we don't פסקן
pasken this at all and therefore it is not a problem but
it is fascinating this opinion that it is a ממזר. mamzer. Okay.
So that's one approach. So
the but what's the story about בנות ירושלים? Bnos Yerushalayim? So אלא
למאן דאמר משום בנות ירושלים כמאי היא? ela l'man d'amar mishum Bnos
Yerushalayim k'mai hi? What's the story about בנות ירושלים? Bnos Yerushalayim? So
פליגי בה רב יוסף ורבנן. pligi bah Rav Yosef v'rabbanan. It's a
debate of רב יוסף Rav Yosef and רבנן. rabbanan.
It's not really much of a debate as we're going to see.
תרווייהו משמיה דרבה בר בר חנה travaihu mishmei d'Rabbah bar bar Channah
and both in the name of רבה בר בר חנה. Rabbah bar
bar Channah. חד אמר תריסר אלפי גברי ושישתא אלפי קשתאי. chad amar
treisar alfei gavrei v'shishta alfei kashtai. One said 12,000 men and 6,000
archers. And one said twelve thousand men and among them six thousand
archers. That’s not a big deal anyway, but we’re talking about all
of these men as we’re gonna see that were part of the
destruction of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, whether twelve thousand or eighteen
thousand. בשעה שנכנסו עובדי כוכבים להיכל, Besha'at shenichnesu ovdei kochavim laheichal,
when the non-Jews came into the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash to destroy
it, הכל נפנו על כסף וזהב, hakol nifnu al kesef vezahav, everybody
else went to the gold and the silver. והם, Vehem, and this
group of twelve thousand or eighteen thousand men, נפנו על בנות ירושלים,
nifnu al benot Yerushalayim, they went to seize to rape the young
women of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. שנאמר: Shenemar: נשים בציון עינו, Nashim beTzion inu,
the women of Jerusalem were, you know, were oppressed, which actually, you
know, is a word that means were raped. בתולות בערי יהודה. Betulot
be'arei Yehuda. So
basically it's the same, I mean, halachically it's the same idea that
this idea was products of non-Jews and Jewish women. Were the non-Jews
עבדי שלמה, avdei Shlomo, were the non-Jews the non-Jews that destroyed the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash that raped these Jewish women? But they were
products of non-Jewish men and Jewish women. And therefore the question is
what is the status of these people? So according to one opinion,
no problem, right? Non-Jewish man, Jewish woman, the kids are Jewish, no
problem. But according to another approach, which is the one that has
that sees problems in תרמוד, Tarmo, the issue is that no, even
with a Jewish mother, if it's a non-Jewish father the child is
a ממזר. mamzer. Again, we don't פוסקן pasken that way, פוסקן pasken
that the child is not problematic, okay? But this is, there is
an interesting debate I should say by the way, which comes up,
which is whether the child is still a problem if the child
is a girl for a כהן. kohen. And that's a big issue.
Nobody says it's דאורייתא, de'oraita, maybe it's not even דרבנן, de'rabbanan, but
there might be this concept of פגום לכהן pagum le'kohen and this
actually comes up a lot, you know, because nowadays there's a lot
of cases of mixed marriage and you have a Jewish mother, so
they say okay, Jewish mother, kid, not a problem, right? End of
story. So we certainly don't פוסקן pasken this גמרא, Gemara, this opinion
that it's a ממזר. mamzer. But it's not end of story because
if she wants to marry a כהן, kohen, that child, there are
some issues that have to be, you know, looked at. I mean,
so there is some debate about that. Okay, so this is the
opinion that the child of a non-Jewish man and a Jewish mother
is a ממזר, mamzer, either like תוספות Tosfot says because of רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva of איסור לאו, issur lav, or the other opinion
has nothing to do with the איסור, issur, it has to do
with the lack of possibility of קידושין. kiddushin. Either way, we don't
rule that way, we rule that the child is Jewish, no problem.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now we're going
to digress a little and then come back to this theme.
Okay, אמר רב שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן, amar Rav Shmuel
bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan, פסוק זה, pasuk ze, the following פסוק,
pasuk, שר העולם אמרו. sar ha'olam amro. The
שר העולם, sar ha'olam, the I don't know, angel of the world
or the steward of the world said. Now what exactly this refers
to, who is שר העולם sar ha'olam is not clear, but there's
a strong inclination to think that the גמרא Gemara is referring to,
it's not God as we'll see in a minute, to מטטרון, Metatron,
which is seen as some heavenly angel that might actually be like
God's right-hand man or some even embodiment of God. Anyway, ask a
Kabbalist, I'm just going to read the next lines, and you're not
at the level for me to really tell you what's going on
here. שנאמר, Shenemar, okay, נער הייתי גם זקנתי, Na'ar hayiti gam zakanti,
remember that was a פסוק pasuk we quoted yesterday, I was a
youth and even grew old. So מאן אמרה, man amrei, who said
it? אילימא קודשא בריך הוא, Ileima Kudsha Brich Hu, if God is
saying it, מי איכא זקנה קמיה? mi ika zikna kamey? God wouldn't
say I've grown old. We might envision God as an old man,
you know, but God would not say of himself I've grown old.
So אלא דוד אמר, ela David amar, so okay David. No, מי
קשיש כולי האי? mi kashish kulei hai? David wasn't so old that
he should say גם זקנתי. gam zakanti. So אלא שמע מינה, ela
shema mina, couldn't be God, couldn't be David, it must be שר
העולם אמרו. sar ha'olam amro. All right. I don't know, moving on.
Okay, that's really not relevant for us. Let's get to the next
line which is more connecting to this idea of the raping of
the daughters of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ואמר רב שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי
יונתן: Ve'amar Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan: מאי דכתיב, mai
dichtiv, what's meant by the verse, ידו פרש צר על כל מחמדיה,
yado parash tzar al kol machmadeha, the enemy stretched out over all
of its desirous things, over ירושלים Yerushalayim and the destruction of the
בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? So who is this צר? tzar? זה עמון
ומואב. Ze Amon uMoav. בשעה שנכנסו Besha'at shenichnesu עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim
להיכל, laheichal, when the non-Jews entered the Temple, הכל נפנו על כסף
וזהב, hakol nifnu al kesef vezahav, everybody went to gold and silver.
והם נפנו על ספר תורה, Vehem nifnu al sefer Torah, that's the
מחמדיה, machmadeha, the most desirous thing is a ספר תורה. sefer Torah.
אמרו, Amru, they said, what just happened? Hold on,
something weird just happened.
I don't know, my whole thing stopped. You, I don't know, hold
on, where was it? Yeah, is it back?
No, oh gosh, okay, my computer's restarting itself. Okay, keep on moving.
All right, והם, vehem, הכל נכנסו להיכל, hakol nichnesu laheichal,
הכל נפנו על כסף וזהב, hakol nifnu al kesef vezahav, והם נפנו
על ספר תורה. vehem nifnu al sefer Torah. They turned to the
ספר תורה, sefer Torah, that's מחמדיה. machmadeha. אמרו, Amru, they said, זה
שכתוב בו, ze shekativ bo, this that is written in it... that
it's written by it. לא יבוא עמוני מואבי בקהל השם lo yavo
Amoni Moavi bi-kehal Hashem that we cannot enter into the congregation of
God, so עמון Amon and מואב Moav then they're ישרפו באש yisrefu
ba-esh will be burnt in a fire. Now the מהרש"א Maharsha points
out that the word פרס Paras read backwards is שרס Saras and
that's part of the play on words that's being made here. Also
though, the פסוק pasuk by איכה Eicha also says, right, אשר צוית
לא יבאו בקהלך, asher tzivita lo yavo'u bi-kehalekha, the enemy came into
the temple, the enemy that you said shall not enter into your
congregation. That's in the פסוק pasuk in איכה. Eicha. You remember that
פסוק? pasuk? Yes. Alright. Should I read it? Anyway, so that's the
דרשה drasha that is being made. Those people who are not allowed
to be part of the קהל, kahal, so in the simple sense
of איכה Eicha it's just saying that they entered into the temple,
these are people that are rejected from the community and they entered
into the היכל. heichal. But who is it says they cannot go
בקהל השם? bi-kehal Hashem? It's עמון Amon and מואב. Moav. So it's
reading, so it's picking up on that hint and reading that the
מחמדה machmada was the ספר תורה Sefer Torah that they were found
that they were being, you know, that was rejecting them and that's
what they attacked and that's what they then burned. Okay. And that's
ידו פרס צר yado paras tzar and the play of the word
פרס Paras and שרס. Saras. Alright, so let's just move on. I
can't find the פסוק pasuk right now.
Okay. So moving on. אשר צוית לא יבאו בקהלך. asher tzivita lo
yavo'u bi-kehalekha.
There you go. Thank you. So the end of the פסוק pasuk
is אשר צוית לא יבאו בקהלך. asher tzivita lo yavo'u bi-kehalekha. All
right. Now,
צוה השם, tziva Hashem, so again continuing this mode, צוה השם ליעקב
סביביו צריו, tziva Hashem le-Yaakov sivivav tzarav, God commanded for יעקב Yaakov
that the enemies would surround it. אמר רב, amar Rav, כגון הומניא
ופום נהרא, kegon Humanya ve-Fum Nahara, like the city of הומניא Humanya
that is nearby פום נהרא. Fum Nahara. And as רש"י Rashi points
out, הומניא Humanya was peopled by, populated by the Greeks, and פום
נהרא Fum Nahara by the Jews, and apparently the Greeks in that
city were very oppressive over the Jews. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב
אסי. amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav Assi. Fine. Back to what we're
talking about. So now we've established that there was this question about
this whole place called תרמוד, Tarmod, and according to those that it
was a problem, it was because the people there were descendants of
Jewish women and non-Jewish men. And if it was a problem, it
was because one would think that the children would be ממזרים mamzerim
of those type of things, which as we said we do not
פוסקים, pasken, but it is an idea of ממזרות mamzerus as a
product not of an איסור כרת issur kares but a product of
a
union which marriage is not possible. So now the גמרא Gemara continues.
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב אסי, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav Assi,
עובדי כוכבים, akum, now if that was radical to you, the idea
of ממזרות mamzerus in that context, wait until you read this. אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב אסי, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav Assi, עובדי
כוכבים שקידש בזמן הזה, akum she-kideish bi-zman ha-zeh, a non-Jew who marries
a Jewish woman nowadays, חוששין לקידושין, chosheshin le-kidushin, you are concerned that
it might be a binding קידושין. kidushin. Why? שמא מעשרת השבטים הוא,
shema me-aseret ha-shevatim hu, maybe this non-Jew is really just a descendant
of the ten tribes, and therefore anybody who's a non-Jew might be
a Jew. Okay, so all right, that's what the גמרא Gemara is
going to ask. So therefore, maybe he's a Jew and you have
to be concerned. מתיבי, mativei, כל דפריש מרובא פריש. kol de-parish me-rubah
parish.
Don't we say anybody who separates, separates from the רוב? rov? And
the majority of the non-Jews are non-Jews. Excuse me. So therefore, why
this crazy concern? אמר רב, amar Rav, no, בדוכתא דקביע. be-duchta de-kavia.
We're talking about a place where they are fixed, which means in
a place where we know the ten tribes were exiled, if somebody
marries a person who even if everybody there identifies as non-Jews, if
you know that was the place that the ten tribes were exiled
to, then you have to be concerned that the people there still
might be descendants of the ten tribes. Okay? דאמר רבי אבא בר
כהנא, de-amar Rabbi Abba bar Kahana, וינחם, va-yanchem, or I think it's
וינחם בחלח ובחבור, va-yanchem be-Chalach u-ve-Chavor, this is by סנחריב Sancheriv where
he put the ten tribes where he dispossessed, where he relocated them
to, בחלח ובחבור נהר גוזן וערי מדי. be-Chalach u-ve-Chavor nehar Gozan ve-arei
Madai. So what are these places? So חלח זו חלזון, Chalach zo
Chalazon, וחבור זו חדיב, ve-Chavor zo Chadyav, top of י"ז עמוד
א'. yud-zayin amud aleph. נהר גוזן זו גינזק nehar Gozan zo Ginzak
וערי מדי זו חמדן. ve-arei Madai zo Chemdan. So now you know.
So if you ever, if a non-Jew from those places ever marries
a Jewish woman, then because that was the location that the ten
tribes were exiled to, you have to be concerned that that person
might actually be descendant of the ten tribes. ואיכא דאמרי, ve-ika d-amri,
and some say one minute, ואיכא דאמרי ve-ika d-amri and some say
זו ניהר וחברותיה. zu Nihar ve-chaveroteiha. Okay, this is ניהר Nihar and
its surrounding cities. חברותיה מאן, chaveroteiha man, so what are its surrounding
cities? אמר שמואל, amar Shmuel, כרך מושכי חידקי ודומקייא. krach Mushkhei Chidki
ve-Dumkaya. All right, so now you know. Those are the places that
the non-Jews might be situated. Now, we've just stopped there for a
minute, we'll say, okay, that doesn't say anything, I mean, okay, besides
this idea that there still might be descendants from the ten tribes
in those places, it didn't say anything radical about the idea of
personal status, okay? But now let me ask you a question. One
minute. If there's a descendant of the ten tribes, so what are
we assuming in terms of the ways in which they descended? Are
we assuming that those ten tribes men and women all married amongst
themselves and they descended that way, or are we assuming that maybe
they intermarried with non-Jews, but we're concerned that these people here would
be descendant from
the
So that's what we would say. If you're concerned that they might
be from the ten tribes, even in a possibility of intermarriage, it
means you're concerned that somebody's great, great, great, great, great grandmother, all
matrilineal, was Jewish, right? Reasonable concern. Fine. That's what תוספות Tosfos says,
or at least one approach of what תוספות Tosfos says. Now, to
blow your mind, let's read רשי. Rashi. עשרת שבטים הוא Asaret Shevatim
hu about six lines from the bottom on דף טז עמוד ב.
daf tet zayin amud bet. So רשי Rashi says שנסו עובדות כוכבים
shenasu ovdot kochavim that the Jews there, the Jewish men, marry non-Jewish
women in these places. So it was Jewish father, not Jewish mother.
וקסבר דעובדת כוכבים שילדה מישראל הולד ממזר וחוששין לקידושי ממזר. ve-kasvar de-ovedet
kochavim she-yaldah mi-Yisrael ha-velad mamzer ve-chosheshin le-kidushei mamzer. And
we're of the opinion here that a child that has a Jewish
father and a non-Jewish mother is Jewish and is a ממזר, mamzer,
patrilineal descent. So רשי Rashi understands, so I mean we're going to
see the גמרא Gemara is going to continue. So רשי Rashi understands
that there is an opinion in the גמרא Gemara that patrilineal descent
produces a ממזר, mamzer, not a non-Jew. Now, if you had to
take your choice between, it's not like oh there's an opinion in
the גמרא Gemara that we can go by patrilineal descent. Yes! Okay,
so we've solved the whole problem of intermarriage. No, actually if you
had to take your choice as we'll see, it's better to be
non-Jew and then you can convert as opposed to ממזר mamzer where
you're stuck. But it still is shocking that there's this possibility of
patrilineal descent, that's what רשי Rashi is reading that you're still Jewish.
Now, תוספות Tosfos is of course shocked. תוספות Tosfos says, what are
you talking about? I mean you know, it's clear that we from
all from many משניות Mishnayot not just גמרות, Gemarot, that a patrilineal
descent is not Jewish. What are you talking about, רשי? Rashi? So
תוספות Tosfos has two answers. One answer of תוספות Tosfos is עובד
כוכב שקידש בזמן הזה. oved kochav she-kidesh be-zman ha-zeh. So תוספות Tosfos
has two answers while I'll just tell it to you and then
we'll read it inside. Answer number one is that if you're of
the opinion we just said a minute ago that Jewish mother and
non-Jewish father make a ממזר mamzer because קידושין kidushin is not possible,
so maybe he says the same would be true in the mirror
image, meaning if you buy into the idea that that union creates
a ממזר, mamzer, so then your basic take is Jew plus non-Jew
is not a question of Jewish or not Jewish, it's fundamentally ממזר.
mamzer. And maybe it's true with a Jewish mother, no קידושין, kidushin,
but again it's a little funny why that should work in parallel,
but he says maybe that's the idea. So if you said ממזר
mamzer in the case of Jewish mother and non-Jewish father, maybe you'll
say ממזר mamzer in the reverse. So this would follow that opinion.
But since as we said in the case of Jewish mother and
non-Jewish father we don't say ממזר, mamzer, we say Jew, so then
it's not about ממזר, mamzer, it's about identity and then in the
reverse we'll say non-Jew. So that's תוספות Tosfos first explanation. Yes, maybe
רשי Rashi is right, maybe that is what's being assumed here, but
that's only if you, and רשי Rashi himself said ממזר, mamzer, it's
only if you assume in one of these mixes that it's ממזר,
mamzer, then it could be ממזר mamzer both ways. The other thing
תוספות Tosfos says is that no, we're just assuming that they're descendant
from Jewish women, non-Jewish fathers but it's a matrilineal descent, and that's
the issue why we're assuming that they might still be Jewish. So
let's just read that in תוספות. Tosfos. עובד כוכב שקידש בזמן הזה.
oved kochav she-kidesh be-zman ha-zeh. So he says פירש בקונטרס דקסבר עובדת
כוכבים שילדה מישראל הולד ממזר וחוששין לקידושי ממזר. peirush be-kuntres de-kasvar ovedet
kochavim she-yaldah mi-Yisrael ha-velad mamzer ve-chosheshin le-kidushei mamzer. ותימא דבכמה משניות מוכח
דאין היחס אלא אחריה.
u-teimah de-ve-kama mishnayot mu-chach de-ein
ha-yachas ela achareha. A
non-Jewish father, a Jewish father, non-Jewish mother, it goes by the mother.
דתנן לקמן מי שיש לו בן מכל מקום de-tnan le-kaman mi she-yesh
lo ben mikol makom etc. etc. he goes through all the proofs.
וניראה דלא קשיא כל כך, ve-nireh de-lo kashya kol kach, it's the
line starts with the words ודלא קשיא. ve-delo kashya. ודלא קשיא כל
כך דהא נמי משנה היא סבירא ליה דעובד כוכב ועבד הבא על
בת ישראל הולד כשר.
de-ha nami mishnah hi savira lei de-oved kochav ve-eved ha-ba
al bat Yisrael ha-velad kasher. Okay, so והוא הדין איפכא. ve-hu ha-din
ipcha. So if you assume that a Jewish mother non-Jewish father produces
a כשר kosher Jew, so in the reverse the child will also
be כשר, kosher, just not Jewish. Okay, and that's the way we
do it. דרב אסי סבר כרבי עקיבא de-Rav Assi savar ke-Rabbi Akiva
דאמר אין קידושין תופסין בחייבי לאוין והולד ממזר. de-amar ein kidushin tofsin
be-chayvei lavin ve-ha-velad mamzer. And והוא הדין ve-hu ha-din and so if
it's true הולד ממזר ha-velad mamzer with a Jewish mother, it's also
going to be true הולד ממזר ha-velad mamzer with a Jewish father
and a non-Jewish mother exactly.
It's not a ממזר mamzer at all,
no, the כהן Cohen issue is distinct. And then in the end
תוספות Tosfos just says that the real answer is
that if you look at the word that starts with the word
יהודה. Yehuda. וניראה דטעמיה דרבי יהודה אמר רב אסי משום בנות. ve-nireh
de-tameih de-Rabbi Yehuda amar Rav Assi mishum banot. Okay, no, his reason
isn't because of Jewish fathers, his reason is because of Jewish mothers.
Alright, so again to repeat because I know I'm doing this fast
and also just give me one second here because this stupid thing
had to be restarted.
Sorry, just one second.
Am I talking fast enough today? Okay, so... So, we have a
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* that says that the people are descendant or come
from this city where the ten tribes were moved
to, that they might be Jewish. How would you say they might
be Jewish if there was obviously intermarriage going on? So we would
have said, well maybe cause great-great-great-great-great grandmother all the way matrilineal was
Jewish, you know, and sometimes you have stories like that. Fine, that's
what תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says at the end, that that's the way
to read the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but the earlier possibility was no,
they actually the reason they might be Jewish is because of Jewish
fathers and not Jewish mothers, and that's crazy, that's patrilineal descent. תוספות
*Tosafos* says okay, but if we assume that in the reverse case
of Jewish mother and non-Jewish father it's ממזר mamzer. *mamzer*, which is
what we saw earlier, which we don't פוסקן *pasken* like, then the
same would be true in the mirror image that yes you would
have an idea of patrilineal descent except the kid would be a
ממזר mamzer, *mamzer*, which is worse than not Jewish because then there's
no solution to that. Okay, so that's what תוספות *Tosafos* says is
following רש"י Rashi *Rashi* is one way of reading this גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. So now we have two new radical ideas which are interlinked,
which is anytime one parent is not Jewish the child is a
ממזר mamzer, *mamzer*. Okay, which is crazy, that's not what we're used
to thinking, we don't פוסקן *pasken* that way, but that is what
the assumptions are that are being made here, as opposed to saying
no, no issue of ממזרות mamzerut, *mamzerus*. Jewish mother child is Jewish
no ממזר *mamzer* problem, Jewish father child is not Jewish also no
ממזר *mamzer* problem, that's what we think. But this approach says any
mix, one Jewish parent one non-Jewish, child is Jewish and a ממזר
*mamzer*.
Yes. So what you're saying is right, but in the end if
it's a Jewish mother and non-Jewish father the ולד *vlod* is כשר
*kasher*, not even a ממזר *mamzer*, right?
Correct, yeah, the only question was פגום לכהונה *pagum lekehuna*, which is
an issue we'll see. Yes,
you got a question? Yes.
If the sense of ממזר *mamzer* is like this huge irreparable problem
why would you ever like look for ways to impose it?
It seems like... You wouldn't.
No, they're not looking, they're just saying that that's their הלכתי *halakhic*
position. Not like they're trying, it's just if you come with that
assumption that's what you have. Okay, so that is some quite radical
idea about what happens with a Jewish father according to the way
רש"י *Rashi* reads it, a Jewish father and a non-Jewish mother. So
let's continue in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* top of י"ז עמוד amud
א' *Yud Zayin Amud Aleph*. So we have like this. כי אמריתה
*Ki amritay*,
so this was רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* reporting in the name of
רב אסי *Rav Assi*. Then he says when I said this over
קמי דשמואל *kamei deShmuel* in front of שמואל *Shmuel*, אמר amar לי
*amar li*, he said to me, no, בנך הבא מן הישראלית קרוי
בנך bincha haba min hayisraelit kari bincha, *bincha haba min haYisraelis kari
bincha*. And now this is what we are familiar with, this is
crazy. If it's your son that comes from a Jewish woman, is
your son. ואין בנך bincha הבא מן העובד כוכבים קרוי בנך kari
bincha אלא בנו ella bino, *v'ein bincha haba min ha'oved kokhavim kari
bincha ela b'no*, her son.
Which basically means, hey buddy, matrilineal descent. Okay, so which explains right
why why how רש"י *Rashi* why רש"י *Rashi* read the earlier גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* like he did because that's how what this is responding
to. So the earlier גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumed Jewish father the kid
is Jewish, okay, and the way רש"י *Rashi* said it's a ממזר
*mamzer*. That by the way the ממזר *mamzer* point wasn't in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* was just a could have
just been saying Jewish, but and the response is we do not
have to be concerned about the intermarried descendants about the descendants of
the intermarried ten tribes because if we're dealing with Jewish fathers then
the kids are not Jewish. Okay, yes.
The שמואל *Shmuel*, wasn't שמואל's *Shmuel's* daughters kidnapped and raped and had
children by the by the rapists?
Okay,
so that
that would be something appropriate to ask שמואל *Shmuel*.
Oh, oh, I see your point. Oh, interesting. Okay, you're right, I
wasn't thinking about that, that's a good point. Okay, so anyway, so
this is the classic response that in a case of Jewish father
and non-Jewish mother, excuse me, yes, in case of Jewish father and
non-Jewish mother don't go tell me the kids are Jewish, the kids
are not Jewish. Now what does this mean בנך bincha הבא מן
העובד כוכבים *bincha haba min ha'oved kokhavim* etc.? What are we sort
of talking you know what it seems like he's referring to something.
So I'll just say quickly I mean there's another גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
that spells this out but this is it's important like we're talking
about matrilineal descent we might as well tell you what the basic
פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is that we base this whole idea on. Turn
this here, where's my okay where's my thing here? So the פסוק
pasuk. *pasuk* is whatever what is it? בתך לא תקח לבנך *bitcha
lo tikach lebanacha*, what is it? בתך לא תקח לבנך *bitcha lo
tikach lebanacha*...
I'm trying to see what's the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*... בתך *bitcha*
what is it? Hold on, it's דברים ז' *Devarim Zayin*, ולא תתחתן
בם
*v'lo titchaten bam*,
do not intermarry with them right? בתך לא תתן לבנו *bitcha lo
titein livno*. ובתו לא תקח u'vito lo tikach, לבנך,
ובתו לא
תקח, right, because you see by the way the פסוק pasuk is
being written here, the daughter always goes, the woman goes where the
man is. So don't take his daughter for your son and your
daughter don't give to his son. Daughter goes where the man is.
Why? Why should you not do that? כי יסיר את בנך מאחרי.
Ki yasir et bincha me'acharai.
Now
there's a problem with this פסוק. pasuk כי יסיר Ki yasir is
male.
So which man is going to cause your son to leave me?
Right? It could be כי תסיר את בנך מאחרי, Ki tasir et
bincha me'acharai, right,
the daughter, the non-Jewish women will take your son away. Or it
could be כי יסיר את בתך מאחרי, Ki yasir et bitcha me'acharai,
the non-Jewish man will take your daughter away. But what is the
man will take your son away? What does that mean? So the
Rabbis say what it means is that בנך is not your son,
בנך is your grandson. Okay? And therefore the non-Jewish man who
marries who marries the Jewish woman, okay, a Jewish woman, will take
your grandson away from me, but that will be your grandson because
he'll be Jewish. Okay? So if you have if you give your
daughter, which is the immediate previous
פסוק, pasuk no wait, no I'm sorry it's not that one, it
is actually going back to this. Okay. If the non-Jewish man takes
your daughter then he will take your grandson, your Jewish grandson away
from me. However, that is not a problem if your daughter you
give to their son,
no I keep on getting the wrong, your daughter their daughter you
take, your son takes their daughter, marries a non-Jewish woman, then there's
no concern of leading your grandson astray because your grandson isn't Jewish
to begin with. So based on the כי יסיר, Ki yasir, what
does this mean? The male will take your male son away? We
read that as when a non-Jewish man is with a Jewish
woman then the then the child is Jewish and the non-Jewish father
will take your grandson away. And that's what the פסוק pasuk, means
here, just to read how that's implicit here, back to the גמרא.
Gemara So back to the גמרא Gemara it says, right, בנך הבא
מן הישראלית קרוי בנך, kari bincha your son that meaning your grandson
right that comes from the Jewish woman with the non-Jewish man, that's
your son, that's Jewish. ואין בנך הבא מן העובדת כוכבים קרוי בנך
אלא בנו,
v'ein bincha haba
min ha-ovedet kochavim kari bincha ela bino, but a child from a
non-Jewish woman and a Jewish man, that's not קרוי בנך אלא בנו,
and that's why the Torah is not concerned that the non-Jewish mother
will take your grandson away because it won't be your grandson, he
won't be Jewish, he won't be Jewish, yeah.
That passage is specifically referring to the seven nations of Canaan.
Right, so there's a question whether it's referring to דווקא davka the
seven nations or all non-Jews, but it's still understood whatever it's prohibiting
that it's framing the assumption of Jewish identity. So this פסוק pasuk.
is the פסוק pasuk that they hinge this idea on that it
goes by matrilineal descent. Okay, that's a lot to hinge on a
יוד, yud, but that's what they hinged it on. All right? Now
let's say.
Yeah. Is it the father, the מחותן Machutan as it were, is
the male? Right, and in that case it's opposite.
Right, and he'll take your son away because he's a זר. zar.
Right. So תוספות deals, plays with some of those possibilities. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says ואמר רבינא Ve'amar Ravina ויקח בנות. Va-yika banot.
So the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
that's all very nice, but some of those people might be descended
from... so it's very nice that we say, oh, we don't have
to worry about ten tribes because all the kids from the non-Jewish
mothers are not Jewish. But what about the Jewish mothers who were
part of the ten tribes? Maybe some of the kids are descended
from Jewish mothers? So the גמרא Gemara says ואמר רבינא, ve'amar Ravina,
שמע מינה, shma mina, בן בתך הבא מן העובדת כוכבים ben bitcha
haba min ha-ovedet kochavim no בן בתך הבא מן העובד כוכבים קרוי
בנך. ben bitcha haba min ha-oved kochavim kari bincha. And
and we know, so if they're descended from Jewish mothers and with
non-Jewish husbands, Ravina says that I mean this is pretty implicit from
the previous statement that that your the son of your daughter בן
בתך הבא מן העובד כוכבים ben bitcha haba min ha-oved kochavim I
mean meaning who your son of your daughter who had sex with
a non-Jewish man, so the case of a Jewish mother and a
not-Jewish father קרוי בנך is your son. Okay? So very nice, we
go by only matrilineal descent, not patrilineal descent, and therefore we don't
have to be concerned that these descendants of the ten tribes might
be Jewish because the fathers who cares that the fathers were Jewish
the mothers weren't. This says well but maybe the mothers were Jewish,
right? Maybe their maternal great-great-great grandmother... was Jewish? So why aren't we
concerned? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, גמירי *Gemiri*, we have
a tradition, דבנשא דהדורא *de-b'nesha de-hadora*, the women of that generation of
the ten tribes that were exiled, אישתרויי אישתרו *ishtaruei ishtaru*. They were,
רש"י *Rashi* says it means basically their wombs were somehow burst. Somehow
they were infertile. Okay, so we have a tradition that nobody came
out of the Jewish women of the ten tribes. Any descendants of
the ten tribes are only from Jewish men. Okay, which is quite
interesting because some people in their sort of like eschatological vision have
that the ten tribes get restored, and so on according to this,
it's not possible for the ten tribes to get restored. There's no
descendants of the Jewish women from the ten tribes, they're only descendants
of the Jewish men. What? They all convert. What?
Is that listed or? No, that's just a—yeah.
I mean, I don't know what that means, yeah.
Didn't the רדב"ז *Radbaz* rule that the Ethiopians were שבט דן *shevet
Dan*?
Yeah,
so
I don't know, maybe, maybe here he read the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
דוקא davka *davka* about, you know, as a general statement, I'm not
sure. But it's a good point, right? You deal with the—there are
these discussions about the Ethiopians and descendants of—true. So איכא דאמרי *ika
d'amri*, some say, כי אמריתה קמיה דשמואל אמר לי לא זזו משם
עד שעשאום עובדי כוכבים גמורים *ki amrita kamei de-Shmuel amlei lo zazu
misham ad she-asam ovdei kochavim gemurim*. That some say when I told
this to שמואל *Shmuel* that there's an opinion that says that the
people in those places might be descendants from the ten tribes, then
שמואל *Shmuel* said, nope, they did not move from there until they
made them completely as non-Jews. So who's the 'they' who made them
as non-Jews? Does it mean there was a הלכה *halakhic* ruling that
they were non-Jews for the reason we said before? Because they were
all descendants from non-Jewish mothers? Not clear. But now we're going to
see a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, שנאמר she'ne'emar, *shena'amar*, as the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* says, בה' בגדו *ba-Hashem bagadu*, they rejected God, כי בנים זרים
ילדו *ki banim zarim yaladu*, they gave birth to non-Jewish children, or
to foreign children. So does that mean that they had assimilated so
much that they lost their Jewish identity? Right? That would be one
way of reading it, which would also be pretty radical, but there
are those who have suggested reading it that way. Or is this
just another way of resaying what we said before? The kids were
not Jewish. Why were the kids not Jewish? Because it was all
Jewish men with non-Jewish women. And since all of the kids were
not Jewish, it wasn't descendants of the Jewish mothers, just descendants of
Jewish fathers. Therefore it was acknowledged that all of the people in
the places where the ten tribes were exiled were all non-Jews, because
none of them had a Jewish, you know, maternal Jewish grandmother, they
all were descendants only from Jewish fathers, not from Jewish mothers. So
we've said some pretty darn radical things in these last few lines.
First, just to recap what we said, we said that according to
one approach, a non-Jewish father and Jewish mother, the child is a
ממזר *mamzer*, even though the תנאי דמכשרי *tna'ei d'machshiri* or anything, but
because קידושין kiddushin, אין תופסין *kiddushin ein tofsim*, we obviously don't פוסק
*pasken* that way, at most it's a question for כהונה *kehuna*. And
we've also said according to the way רש"י *Rashi* read an earlier
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, that the flip is also true, a Jewish—a Jewish
father and not-Jewish mother, the child also a ממזר *mamzer*, not non-Jewish,
also a ממזר *mamzer*. So תוספות *Tosafot* of course says that can't
be possible, it's clearly not the way we פוסק *pasken*, all these
other משניות *Mishnayot* are at most it's only within the idea of
ממזר *mamzer*, if you say ממזר *mamzer* in one direction, you say
ממזר *mamzer* in the other direction. Okay, but it is still shocking
that there's a possible read that even acknowledging that the child's a
ממזר *mamzer* that there's an element of patrilineal descent. That then has
been rejected now on י"ז ע"א *yod zayin amud aleph*, where the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* completely said absolutely not, any descendant of a non-Jewish
mother the child is not Jewish, and the only way you have
a descendant that is Jewish is if Jewish mother, matrilineal all the
way up, and giving the פסוק *pasuk* כי יסיר את בנך *ki
yasir bincha* as the basis for that idea that it's all matrilineal.
Again, that's completely assumed by all the תנאי *Tannaic* material, with or
without the פסוק *pasuk*, that it's all matrilineal. And nevertheless you don't
have to worry about the people in this place of the ten
tribes because maybe they have a matrilineal descent? No, we have a
tradition that the Jewish women were all infertile, and therefore any descendants
are only from Jewish men, not from Jewish women, and therefore they're
all non-Jews. So according to this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, there's no Jews
from the ten tribes that are left. Yes?
That last verse from הושע *Hoshea*,
the context seems to be he's prophesying before the destruction of the
First Temple that everybody was intermarrying.
Oh, that's interesting. Okay. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this: יתיב רב יוסף Yosef, *yasiv Rav Yosef*—alright, so that was
pretty heavy. Now we get to a little bit lighter, but again,
that's a very compressed few lines about Jewish identity that we just
read. יתיב רב יוסף אחוריה דרב כהנא *yasiv Rav Yosef achorei Rav
Kahana*, רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* sat behind רב כהנא *Rav Kahana*, ויתיב
רב כהנא קמיה דרב יהודה *ve-yasiv Rav Kahana kamei de-Rav Yehuda*, and
רב כהנא *Rav Kahana* was in the front row of the class
and he was sitting in front of רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda*. ויתיב
וקאמר *ve-yasiv ve-ka'amar*, and רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* was sitting and saying:
עתידין ישראל דעבדי יומא טבא כי חרבי תרמוד ki charvi Tarmod. *asidin
Yisrael de-avdi yoma tava ki charvi Tarmod*, the Jews will make a
holiday if תרמוד Tarmod. *Tarmod* is destroyed. Why? Because we just learned
before that there's some opinions that the people of תרמוד Tarmod *Tarmod*
might be ממזרים mamzerim *mamzerim*, there's a whole question of are they
ממזרים mamzerim *mamzerim* or are they non-Jews. And רש"י *Rashi* says that
according to the idea that they were ממזרים *mamzerim*, so since there
was... Like a lot of presumably intermarriage with them or other, it
was very problematic that again whether non-Jews or ממזרים, why would people
intermarry? But that's the reality, that there was that they were sort
of seeping into the Jewish community. So it'll be good when that's
destroyed. I don't know if it means the people would be destroyed,
maybe let's say nice, the people would be dispersed. Okay. Anyway, so
the גמרא Gemara says כי חרבי תרמוד. So הא חריב? hachariv?
So what do you mean? What are you bothered? It is already
destroyed. No, ההיא תמוד הוה. hahi Tamod hava. No, no, no, the
city that was destroyed is תמוד, Tamod, not
תרמוד. והאמרינן היינו תרמוד היינו תמוד. v'ha amrinan haynu Tarmod haynu Tamod.
No, no, the same city. But איכפולי דאיכפיל, ichpulei d'ichpal, it like
redoubled, meaning like it got rebuilt after it was destroyed. חריב מהאי
גיסא, chariv m'hai gisa, if one side of the city is destroyed,
יתיב מהאי גיסא, yativ m'hai gisa, then then it gets built up
on the other half. ואי חריב מהאי גיסא, v'i chariv m'hai gisa,
and if that half is destroyed, then יתיב מהאי גיסא yativ m'hai
gisa it gets built up in the first half. So anyway, this
is like a persistent, it's sort of like the צינים ופחים tzinim
u'pachim of the Torah, it's a persistent city that doesn't go away,
that the people there are ממזרים and constantly creates problems for the
Jewish community. And this as I said, what we're learning in this
דף, daf, we've completely departed from discussions of יבום, yibbum, which is
a major focus of מסכת יבמות, Masechet Yevamot, the issue of ממזרים
and Jewish identity and marrying and who's marrying whom and so on.
So this is a little bit of a precursor of very central
themes that we'll be seeing. Okay. What? חרש? charash? Yeah, it should
be definitely, that's probably a ממזר. Well,
that's why I rephrased it as the city should be destroyed and
people should be dispersed. Okay. That was my
rephrasing. יתיב רב המנונא קמיה דעולא. yativ Rav Hamnuna kamei d'Ulla. רב
המנונא Rav Hamnuna was sitting in front of עולא Ulla וקא הוי
בשמעתא v'ka havei b'shma'ata and he was having a challenge, and עולא
Ulla was sort of
asking him challenging questions in the learning. אמר so רב המנונא Rav
Hamnuna said, מה גברא ma gavra what a great person this is,
he has such good questions. מה גברא אילא דמהרפניא מה אעביד ma
gavra ila d'maharfanya ma avvad but imagine how great this person would
be if his city wasn't הרפניא, Harfanya, if he didn't come from
a
questionable descent. Apparently הרפניא Harfanya was a city like תרמוד that there
was, it's not ממזרות, mamzerut, but questions about the יחוס yichus of
that city. So he said, מה גברא ma gavra this guy's such
a big such an important person, too bad that he's from הרפניא,
Harfanya, that's sort of pulling him down. So
the גמרא Gemara said, איכסיף ichsaf he was
embarrassed.
So let me just get sure who's saying this to whom. One
minute, what does רש"י say?
No, I'm sorry, I got it reversed. עולא Ulla was saying this
about רב המנונא. Rav Hamnuna. רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna was in front
of עולא, Ulla, עולא Ulla was the Rebbe, he was saying it
about רב המנונא. Rav Hamnuna. Okay, so he said רב המנונא, Rav
Hamnuna, what a great person he is, too bad that he, imagine
how great he would be were he not from הרפניא. Harfanya. So
רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna got embarrassed. אמר ליה amar lei so עולא
Ulla said to him, כסף גולגלתא להיכא יהבת, kesaf gulgata l'heicha yahavat,
where do you pay your poll tax to?
להיכא יהבת? l'heicha yahavat? אמר ליה לפום נהרא, amar lei l'Pum Nahara,
he says, oh, I pay it to the city of פום נהרא.
Pum Nahara. So presumably that meant that that's, even if you're like
a New York resident or US resident living somewhere else, you still
have to pay some of your taxes back to the US or
to New York or whatever. So apparently he was, רב המנונא Rav
Hamnuna was living in הרפניא, Harfanya, but he paid his taxes to
פום נהרא. Pum Nahara. And you might remember before we mentioned פום
נהרא Pum Nahara as a Jewish city. So he said, אמר ליה
אם כן מפום נהרא את, amar lei im ken mi'Pum Nahara at,
oh, okay, so you really come from פום נהרא, Pum Nahara, you
might have been living in הרפניא, Harfanya, so don't worry, you have
an okay descent. All right. מאי הרפניא? mai Harfanya? What is this
הרפניא? Harfanya? אמר רב זירא, amar Rav Zeira, הר שהכל פונים בו.
har shehakol ponim bo. Now, why is it seen as such a
problematic place and we're going to do a little דרש drash on
the word. הר שהכל פונים בו, har shehakol ponim bo, it's a
city that everybody turns to, meaning everybody, all the פסולים psulim go
to it. Anybody with questionable parentage, they all go to this city
of הרפניא, Harfanya, nobody else wants to marry with them. במתניתא תנא,
b'matnita tana, in a ברייתא Beraita we taught, כל שאין מכיר משפחתו
ושבטו נפנה לשם. kol she'ein makir mishpachto v'shivto nifne l'sham. Again, anybody
with some questionable parentage goes to that city. Other people don't want
to marry if you don't know what your יחוס yichus is. So
here again we see even outside of the question of ממזרות, mamzerut,
nobody's saying ממזרות, mamzerus just לא מכיר משפחתו ושבטו, lo makir mishpachto
v'shivto, nevertheless the high focus on יחוס yichus and knowing exactly where
you come from and who your parents were was a heightened level
of concern and people would not want to marry with those that
had questionable parentage. So we are already as I said touching on
what will be major themes of מסכת יבמות. Masechet Yevamot. אמר רבא,
amar Rava, והיא עמוקה משאול, v'hi amuka mish'ol, it's like deeper than
even the depths, the netherworld. שנאמר, she'ne'emar meaning because it's worse than
being in the netherworld. Being in הרפניא Harfanya is worse than being
in גיהינום. Gehennom. שנאמר because the verse says, מיד שאול אפדם ממות
אגאלם, mi'yad she'ol efdem mi'mavet eg'alem, I will redeem them from the
netherworld, from death I will redeem them. ואילו פסולותיה דהרפניא, v'ilu psuloteha
d'Harfanya, so fine, somebody who's in the netherworld could be saved and
redeemed, but their
invalidity of
הרפניא... Harfanya... פסולי דהרפניא Psulei Deharfanya משום פסולי דמישן. mishum psulei De-Meshan.
Now the Gemara says that the people who were פסול posul in
Harfanya, they came from the people of Meshan, which was a place
that was not as bad, like, but you know some of the
people there had questionable parentage and they wound up going to
Harfanya. ופסולי דמישן Upsulei De-Meshan משום פסולי דתרמוד mishum psulei De-Tarmod were
came from, so you know came from the פסול posul people in
Tarmod, which we had been discussing
before, ופסולי דתרמוד upsulei De-Tarmod משום עבדי שלמה, mishum avdei Shlomo, and
they came from the slaves of Shlomo that had intermarried with the
Jewish women. והיינו דאמרי אינשי, Vehainu de'amri inshi, and that's what people
say: קבא רבא וקבא זוטא Kava rabba vekava zuta מנדר ואזיל minder
ve'azil לשאול, lish'ol, a big measuring box and a small measuring box,
it rolls and it goes to Sheol. ומשאול לתרמוד, Umish'ol le-Tarmod, and
from Sheol it goes to Tarmod because all these places, שאול Sheol
is, as we said, on a higher level. There's redemption from Sheol.
All the places of questionable heritage and ממזרות mamzerus are lower than
Sheol in this image, you know, visually lower. So it goes to
Sheol and from Sheol to Tarmod and from Tarmod to Meshan and
from Meshan to Harfanya. So everything like rolls downhill. So all the
פסולים psulim roll downhill and you get further and further and less
and less able to be redeemed. So it's a very sort of
a depressing type of an image, you know, but in a way
I hope that one could hear a little bit of a subtext
of a little sense of like, you know, of poignancy or of
sympathy, like what it means to be there and to have no
solution, you know, and that is a thing. Obviously, חז"ל Chazal were
very interested in trying to work, you know, with the issue of
ממזרות mamzerus, and find solutions to it and ספק ממזר safek mamzer
is מותר muttar and all those things, but that didn't change the
fact that there was still this heightened concern of ייחוס yichus and
that somebody who really was bad ייחוס yichus was in a way
very much rejected and went to a different city and was completely
cut off and nobody wanted to marry with them. So חז"ל Chazal
were trying to temper that somewhat, but that doesn't change those harsh
realities.
So anyway, so what we have now had in this last עמוד
is a real distillation of a lot of things we'll be seeing:
number one, issues of ממזרות, mamzerus heightened concerns of ייחוס—do yichus we
know who we're marrying with, etc.? In different places, who are people
in different places? That's a big concern that we'll get to. Can
we identify the nature of people from this place and that place
and so on? And this whole issue of Jewish identity. Again, the
idea of one opinion that one Jewish parent creates a ממזר, a
Jew who's a ממזר, whether it's the Jewish mother or Jewish father,
quite shocking in both directions, and the other where the גמרא asserting
what we take for granted, which is the idea of matrilineal descent
and not an issue of ממזרות—either mamzerus you're Jewish or you're not
Jewish, but not a ממזרות issue. Okay, so that's some way to
end this פרק. perek. הדרן עלך חמישה עשר נשים, Hadran alach chamisha
asar nashim, let us try to start getting some headway into the
next פרק. perek. כיצד אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו? Keitzad eshet achiv
shelo haya be'olamo?
What's the scenario of, going back to that early משנה, Mishnah, remember
we had the case of one of the people that there's no—it's
an ערווה—is ervah your brother's wife when the brother wasn't around, right?
Brother's wife is normally the מצוה mitzvah of ייבום, yibbum, but if
the brother was born afterwards,
after the brother died—like if שמעון Shimon is born—let's say ראובן, שמעון,
ולוי. Reuven, Shimon, ve-Levi. Okay, so ראובן Reuven marries a woman, רחל.
Rachel.
לוי Levi isn't born yet. ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon are around.
ראובן Reuven marries רחל. Rachel. ראובן Reuven dies and then לוי Levi
is born. Okay, so in that case, לוי Levi has no מצוה
mitzvah of ייבום yibbum with רחל Rachel because he wasn't alive at
the same time ראובן Reuven was, and therefore רחל Rachel to him
is just brother's wife and is an ערווה. ervah. And now if
רחל Rachel marries שמעון, Shimon, שמעון Shimon does ייבום yibbum with רחל,
Rachel, okay, so in that case and then שמעון Shimon dies, so
then רחל Rachel is ערווה ervah and that's the case of צרת
ערווה, tzarat ervah, right?
Is that clear? Should I do that again? Let's hope people have
that.
ראובן Reuven marries רחל. Rachel. Okay, ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon are
alive. Let's just get rid of this one. ראובן Reuven and שמעון
Shimon are alive. Okay, ראובן Reuven marries רחל. Rachel. Okay, and then
ראובן Reuven dies. That's what happens number one. Then at stage number
two, לוי Levi is born. Okay, so at this stage this is
אשת אח eshet ach because there's no מצוה mitzvah of ייבום. yibbum.
Okay, so she's an ערווה. ervah. Now שמעון Shimon here is married
to שרה, Sarah, it'll keep similar first letters. Okay, so שמעון Shimon
now does ייבום yibbum with רחל. Rachel.
Okay, at stage number three. Okay, so now he's got these two
wives. And then stage number four
is—let's use red—stage number four is שמעון Shimon dies. Okay, so now
לוי, Levi, what's
לוי'ס... Levi's... Alright, let's take a look.
כיצד אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו, Keitzad eshes achiv shelo haya b'olamo,
שני אחים, shnei achim, ראובן ושמעון, Reuven v'Shimon, ומת אחד מהם, u'meis
echad meihem, Reuven dies. ונולד להם אח, v'nolad lahem ach, and then
לוי Levi is born. ואחר כך יבם השני את אשת אחיו, v'achar
kach yibeim hasheni es eshes achiv, and then שמעון Shimon does יבום
yibum with רחל. Rochel. ומת, u'meis, and then שמעון Shimon dies. הראשונה,
harishona, the first one, רחל, Rochel, יוצאה משום אשת אחיו שלא היה
בעולמו, yotzei mishum eshes achiv shelo haya b'olamo, is an ערוה ervah
to לוי. Levi. והשנייה, v'hashniya, and שרה, Sarah, משום צרתה, mishum tzarasah,
is צרת ערוה. tzaras ervah. Now עשה בה מאמר ומת, asah ba
maamar u'meis, so let's say שמעון Shimon did not do יבום. yibum.
Let's say he was planning on doing יבום yibum but he did
מאמר, maamar, which is like a קידושין, kiddushin a rabbinic קידושין kiddushin,
when יבום yibum is intended. So in that type of a case,
right, and then he died. Now is רחל Rochel actually דאורייתא? d'Oraisa?
Is רחל Rochel you know sort of like an ערוה ervah in
the יבום yibum context? דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, רחל Rochel is not part of
the יבום yibum with שמעון. Shimon. שמעון Shimon דאורייתא d'Oraisa was only
married to שרה Sarah and the יבום yibum is only with שרה.
Sarah. Right? רחל Rochel is really irrelevant because this did not really
make them married biblically. But since rabbinically they're married, so רחל Rochel
is now a sort of ערוה יבום ervah yibum because she's quasi-יבום
yibum because of שמעון's Shimon quasi-marriage to her.
So, so, so שרה Sarah is like a quasi-צרת ערוה. tzaras ervah.
The problem is you can't walk away from that situation because biblically
רחל's Rochel out of the picture and he really has a מצוה
mitzvah with שרה. Sarah. So we're not going to let him do
יבום yibum because it's sort of like ערוה ervah and צרת ערוה,
tzaras ervah, but we're not going to let him walk away, so
he's going to have to do חליצה chalitza to שרה Sarah because
that's where his real obligation is. So let's just read that. עשה
בה מאמר, asah ba maamar, if שמעון Shimon did a מאמר maamar
with רחל, Rochel, ומת, u'meis, and then he died, שנייה, shniya, the
second one, meaning שרה, Sarah, חולצת ולא מתייבמת. choletzes v'lo misyabemes. He
has to do חליצה chalitza because he has a real obligation of
יבום yibum to שרה Sarah because רחל Rochel is really not in
the picture, but, but he cannot do יבום yibum because it sort
of looks like a case of צרת ערוה. tzaras ervah. Yes.
Wouldn't that be the case even if he didn't do מאמר maamar
because of the זיקה? zika?
זיקה. zika. So that's a good קשיא kasha and we'll get to
the זיקה zika issue.
But no, it wouldn't, because because that's a זיקה zika that's still
going back to I don't think the זיקה zika there, you're right,
sometimes we make a זיקה zika quasi-קידושין, but not in this case.
But we'll hopefully we'll get back to that. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. אמר רב נחמן, amar Rav Nachman, מאן דתני man
d'sani ראשונה rishona ולא משתבש. v'lo mishtabesh. So if some say ראשונה
rishona trying to describe רחל, Rochel, so there were some that had
the גירסא girsa the first one, meaning רחל, Rochel, and they refer
to her as ראשונה. rishona. That's not a problem. מאן דתני man
d'sani שנייה shniya ולא משתבש. v'lo mishtabesh. Some describe רחל Rochel in
this scenario as שנייה, shniya, but and which sounds wrong. What does
it mean second? She was the first one in the picture. So
let's take a look. But he says that wouldn't be a wrong
text. מאן דתני man d'sani ראשונה rishona ולא משתבש, v'lo mishtabesh, if
you said ראשונה rishona that's not an error. Top of י"ז עמוד
ב'. Yud Zayin amud Beis. מאי ראשונה? mai rishona? ראשונה לנפילה. rishona
l'nefila. It meant that רחל Rochel was the first one that you
started doing יבום yibum with.
ראובן Reuven
died, רחל Rochel here is referred to as the first one. I
said לוי Levi for the first one is an ערוה ervah and
the second one שרה Sarah is a צרת ערוה. tzaras ervah. So
it's referring to רחל Rochel here. It works good because it's always
with the רישא. reisha. It's referring to רחל Rochel as ראשונה. rishona.
Oh look, and שרה Sarah is שנייה. shniya. Okay, very nice. So
that's our משנה, Mishna, okay, ראשונה, rishona, because she's the first one
of the whole mix. So and he says for the ראשונה rishona
he's an ערוה ervah and for the שנייה shniya is צרת ערוה.
tzaras ervah. So מאי ראשונה? mai rishona? ראשונה לנפילה. rishona l'nefila. רחל
Rochel is the first one that started doing יבום. yibum. When ראובן
Reuven died, she was already in the process of יבום. yibum. So
she's the first one we even discuss through this whole process. ומאן
דתני u'man d'sani שנייה, shniya, but if you refer to רחל Rochel
as the second wife, what does it mean second? ולא משתבש, v'lo
mishtabesh, that's not an error. מאי שנייה? mai shniya? שנייה בנישואין. shniya
b'nisuin. Because שמעון Shimon married her after שרה. Sarah. So she'll be
referred to as the second one. The גמרא says who says שמעון
Shimon married her after שרה? Sarah? Maybe he married her first. So
the גמרא says מי לא עסקינן? mi lo askinan? What do you
mean? Who says we're not talking about a case דיבם ואחר כך
נסב? d'yibeim v'achar kach nasav? That maybe שמעון Shimon first did יבום
yibum with רחל Rochel and then he married שרה. Sarah. So how
can you be referring to רחל Rochel as the second wife? What
would second mean?
So אלא מאי שנייה? ella mai shniya? Now what does it mean
second? שנייה בנישואין, shniya b'nisuin, which is a very funny read. So
שנייה shniya does not mean second, שנייה shniya means the one that's
been married twice. So those that had to refer to רחל, Rochel,
it says when שמעון Shimon died לוי, Levi, רחל Rochel is an
ערוה ervah to לוי Levi and referred to as second. What does
it mean second? Why is רחל Rochel second? It means the woman
who's been married twice. Okay, as opposed to שרה Sarah who's been
the woman who's only been married once. Again, that's not exactly what
the word שנייה shniya means, but okay.
So the גמרא says like this, שנייה בנישואין. shniya b'nisuin. אשת אב
eshet av now, fine, that's the end of that. That wasn't so
interesting. Let's get at least a little in terms of the דרשות.
drashot. אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו היכא כתיבא? eshet achiv shelo haya
baolamo heicha ketiva? Where does it say this idea that if the
brother wasn't alive at the same time, there's no מצוה mitzvah of
יבום yibum and therefore it's an ערווה? ervah? So אמר רב יהודה
אמר קרא, amar Rav Yehuda amar kra, the verse says כי ישבו
אחים יחדיו, ki yeshvu achim yachdov, if brothers sit together, שהיתה להם
ישיבה אחת בעולם, shehayta lahem yeshiva achat baolam, they were living together
at the same time. פרט לאשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו, prat leeshet
achiv shelo haya beolamo, if you're born after the brother dies, then
there's no מצוה יבום. mitzvah yibum. That's the word יחדיו. yachdov. Okay,
and that's the דרשה. drasha. Now that we're looking at the פסוק,
we're going to say other things we learn from that פסוק. יחדיו
yachdov means מיוחדים בנחלה, meyuchadim benachala,
they have to be similar in inheritance. פרט לאחיו מן האם, prat
leachiv min haaim, here's where we learn another very important principle. It's
only paternal brother, not maternal because a person inherits through the father.
So if you have a brother, a paternal brother, then you'll inherit
from one another, but not a... but if you have a maternal
brother, you won't inherit. So the word יחדיו yachdov is also teaching
us that they have to be paternal brothers. רבה אמר אחי מן
האב יליף אחוה אחוה מבני יעקב. Raba amar achi min haav yalif
achva achva mivnei Yaakov. No, we learn that idea of paternal brothers
from יעקב's Yaakov sons, right, because they say to יוסף, שנים עשר
אחים אנחנו, shneim asar achim anachnu, and here it says כי ישבו
אחים יחדיו. ki yeshvu achim yachdov. So the sons of יעקב Yaakov
are only brothers, they're only paternal brothers. So that's not maternal. So
from there we learn the idea of brother means paternal. מה להלן
מן האב ולא מן האם אף כאן מן האב ולא מן האם.
ma lehalan min haav velo min haaim af kan min haav velo
min haaim. So the גמרא says ולילף אחוה אחוה מעריות? veleilef achva
achva mearayot? Why don't we learn where it says אחיך achicha like
אשת אחיך eshet achicha by the עריות arayot and we learn later
that that means even even maternal brother. So maybe here too the
מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum is even maternal brother? So the גמרא
says no. דנים אחים מאחים ואין דנים אחים מאחיך. danim achim meachim
veein danim achim meachicha. No, we'd rather learn כי ישבו אחים ki
yeshvu achim from by the case of יעקב's Yaakov children where it
says שנים עשר אחים אנחנו shneim asar achim anachnu and not from
the עריות arayot where it refers to it as אחיך. achicha. It's
not the exact same word. So the גמרא says מאי נפקא מינה?
mai nafka mina? What do I care? אחים achim or אחיך, achicha,
it's close enough. הא תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, ha tana devei Rabbi
Yishmael, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael teaches in the case by צרעת, tzaraat,
one פסוק says ושב הכהן, veshav hacohen, the כהן cohen returns, another
פסוק says ובא הכהן, uva hacohen, the כהן cohen comes, and even
though they're different words, essentially it's referring to the same thing, זו
היא שיבה זו היא ביאה, zo hi shiva zo hi via, that
we can link those two פסוקים psukim because essentially it's the same
act, even though it's different words. So why not learn אחים achim
from אחיך? achicha? So the גמרא says no. הני מילי היכא דליכא
דדמי ליה. hani mili heicha delaika demidami lei. That's when there's nothing
that's a closer match. אבל היכא דאיכא דדמי ליה, aval heicha deika
demidami lei, if there's a closer match, we can learn אחים achim
from אחים achim or we could learn אחים achim from אחיך. achicha.
So in that case מדדמי ליה ילפינן, midadami lei yalfinan, we learn
it from the closer match. So the word אחים achim is learned
from יעקב's Yaakov sons which are all paternal brothers, not from the
עריות arayot which is even a maternal brother. Let's just read a
little bit more, we're like a minute over, but let's just read
a little bit more. ולילף אחוה אחוה מלוט? veleilef achva achva milot?
Why not learn it from לוט? Lot? דכתיב כי אנשים אחים אנחנו.
dechtiv ki anashim achim anachnu. And there אחים achim means even like
a nephew, not even a brother. So maybe that's what the פסוק
is saying? ומסתברא מבני יעקב הוה ליה למילף, umistabra mivnei Yaakov hava
lei lemilef, משום דמיפני. mishum demifnei.
The word by יעקב Yaakov of אחים achim is an extra word,
מכדי הוה ליה למכתב שנים עשר עבדיך בני
אבינו, michdi hava lei lemichtav shneim asar avdecha bnei avinu, why'd it
have to say the word brothers? It could have said we're all
descendant of our father. וכתיב אחים, vechtiv achim, שמע מינה לאפנויי, shma
mina leafnoyei, that's to make it an extra word so to tell
you you learn from there, paternal brothers, and not from לוט Lot
where it more means relative or nephew. Okay, I should say about
the גמרא's possibility that it means nephew, it seems a little absurd
to us, but I forget who it was, whether it was the
Samaritans or others. Again, the whole problem of how do you do
יבום yibum if it's an איסור ערווה, issur ervah, so the one
one of the non-rabbinic sects said that the מצוה mitzvah of יבום
yibum is only by a relative who's not a brother, by like
a case of nephew and they said the word אחים achim is
לאו דוקא, lav davka, אחים achim means like by לוט, Lot, it
means relative, but not brother, and that the מצוה mitzvah of יבום
yibum only applies where there's no איסור ערווה. issur ervah. So the
fact that the גמרא is suggesting it to us maybe seems absurd
but you should actually be aware there were people in the period
of בית שני Bayit Sheni that דוקא interpreted it that way. So
let's just read one more line. So the גמרא says ואיצטריך למכתב
אחים ואיצטריך למכתב יחדיו. veitztrich lemichtav achim veitztrich lemichtav yachdov.
It had to say both. דאי כתב רחמנא אחים, dei ktav rachmana
achim, had it just said brothers, הוה אמינא לילף אחוה אחוה מלוט,
hava amina leilef achva achva milot, learn it from לוט. Lot. וכי
תימא לא מיפני, vechi teima lo mifnei, and you'll say, oh, the
word by לוט Lot isn't extra? No, אהא איפנויי מיפני, aha ifnoyei
mifnei, it is extra. מכדי הוה ליה למכתב רעים, michdi hava lei
lemichtav reim, it could have it could have said to אברהם Avraham
we're friends. וכתיב אחים, vechtiv achim, of course there was a different
point. Anyway שמע מינה לאפנויי. shma mina leafnoyei. Fine. So we're rejecting
what we said before. You could have learned from לוט. Lot. So
אחים achim itself would have not told you only brothers. כתב רחמנא
יחדיו, ktav rachmana yachdov, that's why it says יחדיו, yachdov, המיוחדים בנחלה,
hameyuchadim benachala,
you're in the same inheritance level. Brothers inherit together from their father.
So יחדיו yachdov tells us that אחים achim means brothers and not
other relatives. דאי כתב רחמנא יחדיו. dei ktav rachmana yachdov. הוה אמינא
דמיחדי באבא ובאימא. hava amina demiyachadi be'abba u've'ima. Maybe they share a
mother and a father. So צריכא, tzaricha, so it has to say
אחים achim to tell me no, just like יעקב Yaakov paternal brothers
is enough. והא מהיכא תיתי? vaha meheichatisi?
Why would I have thought that you need to share both a
mother and a father? יבום בנחלה תליא רחמנא. yibum benachala talya rachamana.
יבום yibum is about inheritance. Now that's a fascinating statement, who said
יבום yibum is about inheritance? יבום yibum is about יקום על שם
אחיו המת. yakum al shem achiv hamet. But the גמרא understands that
part of that idea of following in the brother's name is about
taking over the brother's inheritance and being the one like to
the brother-in-law gets the נחלה nachala and passes it on to the
child. So that's a fascinating assumption the גמרא has that יבום yibum
is about inheritance and the first time we're seeing that. ונחלה מן
האב, vanachala min ha'av, and that's the father, so of course the
maternal relationship doesn't matter. ולא מן האם? velu min ha'em? The גמרא
says no, איצטריך, istrich, I still might have not needed it. סלקא
דעתך אמינא, salka deitach amina, הוה חידושו, havo chiddushu, דקמשרי ערוה גביה.
dekamisharei erva gabei. The whole thing is a חידוש, chiddush, right, that
we're allowing עריות. arayos. So אימא, eima, so maybe I'll try to
limit this חידוש chiddush as much as possible. עד דמיחדי באבא ובאימא,
ad demiyachadi be'abba u've'ima, unless it's the closest relationship possible. That we'll
allow. It's ironic, as opposed to saying nephew, let's solve the problem
by making it a more distant relationship. I might have thought that
we'll allow it, it does override, but only in the closest relationship.
So צריכא, tzaricha, so therefore you needed it. So the end of
the idea, we learned the idea that you have to be alive
at the same time and then you go by paternal brothers, you
don't need to share a mother, and the fascinating הוה אמינא hava
amina number one that it might have been talking about a nephew,
which is an interesting solution to the problem, and number two, the
idea that יבום yibum is about נחלה, nachala, which is also a
fascinating assumption.